If you run the learning algorithm
当你运行一个学习算法时（字幕整理，中国海洋大学，黄海广，haiguang2000@qq.com）
and it doesn't do as well
如果这个算法的表现不理想
as you are hoping, almost all
那么多半是出现
the time it will be because
两种情况
you have either a high bias
要么是偏差比较大
problem or a high variance problem.
要么是方差比较大
In other words they're either an
换句话说 出现的情况要么是欠拟合
underfitting problem or an overfitting problem.
要么是过拟合问题
And in this case it's very
那么这两种情况
important to figure out
哪个和偏差有关
which of these two problems is
哪个和方差有关
bias or variance or a bit of both that you
或者是不是和两个都有关
actually have.
搞清楚这一点非常重要
Because knowing which of these
因为能判断出现的情况
two things is happening would give
是这两种情况中的哪一种
a very strong indicator for whether
其实是一个很有效的指示器
the useful and promising ways
指引着可以改进算法的
to try to improve your algorithm.
最有效的方法和途径
In this video, I would like
在这段视频中
to delve more deeply into
我想更深入地探讨一下
this bias and various issue and
有关偏差和方差的问题
understand them better as well
希望你能对它们有一个更深入的理解
as figure out how to look
并且也能弄清楚怎样评价一个学习算法
at and evaluate knows whether or not we might have a bias problem or a variance problem.
能够判断一个算法是偏差还是方差有问题
Since this would be critical to
因为这个问题对于弄清
figuring out how to improve the performance of learning algorithm that you implement.
如何改进学习算法的效果非常重要
So you've already
好的 这几幅图
seen this figure a few times,
你已经见过很多次了
where if you fit two simple
如果你用两个很简单的假设来拟合数据
hypothesis, like a straight line that that underfits the data.
比如说用一条直线 那么不足以拟合这组数据(欠拟合)
If you fit a two complex
而如果你用两个很复杂的假设来拟合时
hypothesis, then that might
那么对训练集来说
fit the training set perfectly but
则会拟合得很好
overfit the data and this
但又过于完美(过拟合)
may be hypothesis of some
而像这样的
intermediate level of complexity,
中等复杂度的假设
of some, maybe degree two
比如某种二次多项式的假设
polynomials are not too low and not too high degree.
次数既不高也不低
That's just right.
这种假设对数据拟合得刚刚好
And gives you the best
此时对应的的泛化误差
generalization error out of these options.
也是三种情况中最小的
Now that we're armed with the
现在我们已经掌握了
notion of training and validation
训练集 验证集和测试集的概念
in test sets, we can understand
我们就能更好地理解
the concepts of bias and variance a little bit better.
偏差和方差的问题
Concretely, let our
具体来说
training error and cross
我们沿用之前所使用的
validation error be defined as
训练集误差和验证集
in the previous videos, just say,
误差的定义
the squared error, the average
也就是平方误差
squared error as measured
即对训练集数据进行预测
on the 20 sets or as
或对验证集数据进行预测
measured on the cross validation set.
所产生的平均平方误差
Now let's plot the following figure.
下面我们来画出如下这个示意图
On the horizontal axis I am
横坐标上表示的是
going to plot the degree of polynomial,
多项式的次数
so as I go the right
因此横坐标越往右的位置
I'm going to be fitting higher and higher order polynomials.
表示多项式的次数越大
So will the left of this figure, where maybe D equals one, we're
那么我们来画这幅图对应的情况,d可能等于1的情况,
going to be fitting very simple figures.Whereas way here on the right of the
是用很简单的函数来进行拟合,而在右边的这个图中
horizontal axis, have much larger values of D. So a much higher degree of
水平横坐标表示有更多更大的d值.表示更高次数的
polynomial. And so here that's going to correspond to fitting. Much more complex
多项式.因此这些位置对应着使用更复杂的
functions to your training set. Let's look at the training error and the cross
函数来拟合你的训练集时所需要的d值。让我们来把训练集误差和交叉
validation error and plot them on this figure. Let's start with the training
验证集误差画在这个坐标中。我们先来画训练集误差
error. As we increase the degree of the polynomial, we're going to be able to fit
随着我们增大多项式的次数，我们将对训练集拟合得
our training set better and better. And so, if D=1 then it's a relatively high
越来越好。所以如果d等于1时，对应着一个比较大的
training error. If we have a very high degree polynomial our training error is
训练误差。而如果我们的多项式次数很高时，我们的训练误差
going to be really low maybe even zero because we'll fit the training set really well.
就会很小，甚至可能等于0，因为可能非常拟合训练集
And so as we increase the degree of polynomial, we find typically that the
所以，当我们增大多项式次数时，我们不难发现
training error decreases. So, I'm going to write J. Subscript three of data there.
训练误差明显下降。这里我写上J下标3来表示训练集误差
Because our training error tends to decrease with the degree of polynomial
因为随着我们对数据拟合所需多项式次数的增大
that we fit to the data. Next let's look at the cross validation error. Or for that
训练误差是趋于下降的。接下来我们再看交叉验证误差
matter, if we look at the test set error we'll get a pretty similar result as if we
事实上如果我们观察测试集误差的话，我们会得到一个和交叉验证误差
were to plot the cross validation error. So, we know that if D=1. We're fitting a
非常接近的结果。所以，我们知道如果d等于1的话
very simple function. And so we may be under fitting the training set. And so
意味着用一个很简单的函数来拟合数据。也就是说
we're going to have a very high cross validation error. If we fit, you know, an
我们会得到一个较大的交叉验证误差。而如果我们用
intermediate degree polynomial, there's, we have a D equals two in our example on
一个中等大小的多项式次数来拟合时，在前一张幻灯片中我们用的d等于2
the previous slide, we're going to have a much lower cross validation error, because
那么我们会得到一个更小的交叉验证误差
we're just fitting, finding a much better fit to the data. And conversely, if D were
因为我们找了一个能够更好拟合数据的次数，同样地，反过来，如果次数d
too high, so if D took on, say, a value of four, then we're getting over fitting, and
太大，比如说d的值取为4，那么我们又过拟合了
so we ended with a high value for cross validation error. So, if you were to. vary
我们又会得到一个较大的交叉验证误差
this smoothly and plot the curve. You might end up with a curve like that. Where,
因此 如果你平稳地过渡这几个点，你可以绘制出一条平滑的曲线，就像这样
that's J.C.V. Of staza. Indicating that you plot J. Tesla's data, you get
我用Jcv(θ)来表示。同样地，如果你画出Jtest(θ)，你也将得到
something very similar. And so, this sort of plot also helps us to better understand
一条类似的曲线，这样一幅图也同时能帮助我们更好地理解
the notions of bias and variance. Concretely, suppose you've applied a
偏差和方差的概念。具体来说，假设你得出了一个
learning algorithm, and it's not performing as well as you were hoping.
学习算法，而这个算法并没有表现地如你期望那么好。
So, if your cross-validation set error, or your test set error is high. How can we
所以你的交叉验证误差或者测试集误差都很大。我们应该
figure out if the learning algorithm is suffering from high bias or if it's suffer
如何判断此时的学习算法正处于高偏差的问题还是
from high variance? So the setting of the cause validation error being high,
高方差的问题？交叉验证误差比较大的情况，
corresponds to either this regime or this regime. So this regime on the left
对应着曲线中的这一端，或者这一端，那么左边的这一端，
corresponds to a high bias problem. That is, if you're fitting a overly low order
对应的就是高偏差的问题。也就是你使用了一个过于小的
polynomial, such as a D=1. When we really needed a higher order polynomial to fit
多项式次数，比如d等于1。但实际上我们需要一个较高的多项式次数来拟合数据
the data. Whereas in contrast, this regime corresponds to a high variance problem.
相反地，右边这一端对应的是高方差问题。
That is, if D, the degree of polynomial was too large for the data set that we
也就是说，多项式次数d对于我们的数据来讲太大了，
have. And this figure just has a clue for how to distinguish between these two
这幅图也提示了我们怎样区分这两种情况。
cases. Concretely for the high bias case.That is the case of under fitting. What we
具体地说，对于高偏差的情况，也就是对应欠拟合的情况，我们
find is that both the cross validation error and the trading error are going to
发现交叉验证误差和训练误差都会
be high. So if your algorithm is suffering from a bias problem. The training set
很大。因此，如果你的算法有偏差问题的话，那么训练集
error, will be high. And you might find that the cross validation error will also
误差将会比较大。同时你可能会发现交叉验证集误差
be high. It might be a close. Maybe just slightly higher than a training error. And
也很大。两个误差可能很接近，或者可能验证误差稍大一点
so, if you see this combination that's a sign your algorithm may be suffering from
所以如果你看到这样的组合情况，那就表示你的算法正处于
high bias. In contrast if your algorithm is suffering from high variance then if
高偏差的问题。反过来，如果你的算法处于高方差的问题，
you look here. We'll notice that J-train that is the training error is going to be
那么如果你观察这里，我们会发现 Jtrain就是训练误差，
low. That is your fitting the training set very well. Where as your, cross validation
会很小。也就意味着，你对训练集数据拟合得非常好。而你的交叉验证误差也一样。
error. Assuming that this is say the squared era. Which we're trying to
假设此时我们最小化的是平方误差，
minimize . Where as in contrast, your error on the cross
而反过来，你的交叉验证集误差
validation set or your cross function in the cross validation set will be much bigger
或者说你的交叉验证集对应的代价函数的值，将会远远大于
Than your training set error. So, there's a double greater than sign. That's the
训练集误差。这里的双大于符号是一个
math symbol for much greater than, denoted by two greater than signs. And so, if you
数学符号，表示远远大于，用两个大于符号表示。因此如果
see this combination of values then that might give you, that's a clue that your
你看见这种组合的情况，这就预示着你的
learning algorithm maybe suffering from high variance. And might be over
学习算法可能正处于高方差和过拟合的情况
emphasizing. And the key that distinguishes these two cases is if you
同时，区分这两种不同情形的关键依据是
have a high bias problem your training set error will also be high. Your hypothesis
如果你的算法处于高偏差的情况，那么你的训练集误差会很大。因为你的假设
is just not fitting the training set well. And if you have a high variance problem.
不能很好地拟合训练集数据。而当你处于高方差的问题时
Your training set error will usually be low. That is much lower than your cross
你的训练误差通常都会很小，并且远远小于
validation error. So hopefully that gives you a somewhat better understanding of the
交叉验证误差。好的，但愿这节课能让你更清楚地理解
two problems of bias and variants. I still have a lot more to say about bias and
偏差和方差这两种问题。在之后几段视频中，我还将对偏差和误差做更多的解释
variants in the next few videos. But what we'll see later is that by diagnosing
但我们之后要关注的是诊断一个学习算法
whether a learning algorithm may be suffering from high bias or high variance,
是否处于高偏差或高方差的情况。
we'll show you even more details of how to do that in later videos. We'll see that by
在后面几段视频中我还将向你展示更多细节，我们将会看到
figuring out whether a learning algorithm may be suffering from high bias or high
通过分清一个学习算法是处于高偏差还是高误差，
variance, or a combination of both, that, that would give us much better guidance
还是两种情况的结合，这能够更好地指引我们
promising things to try in order to improve the performance of a learning algorithm.
应该采取什么样的措施，来提高学习算法的性能表现.